This
is
Aldous
Huxley,
a
man
haunted
by
a
vision
of
hell
on
earth.
A searing
social
critic,
Mr.
Huxley,
years
ago
wrote
Brave
New
World,
a
novel
that
predicted that
someday
the
entire
world
would
live
under
a
frightful
dictatorship.
Today,
Mr.
Huxley
says
that
his
fictional
world
of horror
is
probably
just
around
the
corner
for
all of
us.
We'll find
out why
in a
moment.
The
Mike Wallace
interview,
presented by
the
American
Broadcasting
Company,
in association
with
the Fund
for the
Republic, brings you a special television series discussing
the
problems
of
survival
and
freedom
in
America.
Good
evening,
I'm
Mike Wallace.
Tonight's guest
Aldous Huxley
is a
man of letters
as
disturbing as
he is
distinguished.
Born
in
England
now, a resident
of California, Mr.
Huxley has
written some
of
the most
electric
novels and social
criticism of
this
century.
He's just finished
a
series
of
essays
called,
Enemies
of
Freedom, in which he
outlines and defines
some of
the
threats
to our freedom in
the United
States.
Mr.
Huxley,
right off the bat, let
me ask
you this, as
what
are
the enemies
of
freedom
here
in
the
United
States?
Well,
I don't
think you can
say who
in
the
United
States?
I
don't think there are any sinister persons deliberately trying
to
rob
people of
their
freedom.
But
I
do
think, first
of all,
that there are a number of
impersonal forces which are
pushing
in
the
direction
of
less
and
freedom.
And
I also
think that there
are a number
of technological
devices
which
anybody
who
wishes
to use can use to accelerate this process of going away from freedom of
imposing
control.
What are
these
forces
and
these
devices, Mr.
Huxley?
I should
say
that there
are two
main
impersonal
forces.
The first of
them
is not exceedingly important in the United States at the present time, though very important in other
countries.
This
is the force
which
in general terms can
be
called
overpopulation,
the
mounting
pressure
of
population
pressing
upon
existing
resources.
And
this,
of
course,
is an
extraordinary
thing.
Something
is happening,
which has never
happened
in
the
world's history before. I mean, it's just take a simple fact that between the time of the birth of Christ and the landing of the
Mayflower, the
population
of the
Earth
doubled.
It rose
from 250 million
to
probably 500
million.
Today,
the
population
of the Earth
is rising at such a rate
that it will
double in
half
a
century.
Well, why should
overpopulation
work to
diminish our
freedoms?
Well,
in
a
number
of ways, I mean, the experts in the
field, like Harrison
Brown, for example, pointed
out that in the
underdeveloped countries, actually the standard of living is
present-folding that people have
less
to eat and
less goods
per
capita
than
they
had
years
ago.
And
as
the position of these countries, the economic position becomes more
and
more
precarious, obviously the central government has to take over more and more responsibility for keeping the ship of
state on
an
even
keel.
And
then,
of
course,
you're
likely
to get
social
unrest
under such
conditions
with
again an
intervention
of
the
central
government.
And
so,
I think one sees
here a
pattern
which seems
to
be
pushing
very
strongly
towards
a
totalitarian
regime.
And
unfortunately,
as in
all these
underdeveloped countries, the only highly organized political party is the Communist Party, it looks rather as though they will be the
heirs
to this unfortunate process that
they will step
into the
position
of
power.
Well,
then
ironically
enough, that
one
of the greatest
forces against communism in the world, the Catholic
Church, according to your
thesis, would seem to be pushing us directly into the hands of the Communists
because they are against birth
control.
Well,
I
think
this strange
paradox
probably
is
true.
There
is
an extraordinary situation,
actually.
One
has
to
look at it, of course, from a biological
point of
view.
The
whole
essence
of
biological
life
on
Earth
is
a
question
of
balance.
And
what
we
have done is to
practice death
control in
a most intensive manner without balancing
this with birth
control at the other
end, consequently the birth rates
remain as high as
they
were,
and
death rates
have
fallen
substantially.
All
right, then, so much for the time being anyway for overpopulation,
another
force
that is diminishing our
freedoms.
Well, another
force which
I think is
very strongly
operative
in this country is
the
force of what may be called
overorganization
as
technology
becomes
more
and
complicated.
And
since
the industry
would have more and more elaborate organizations, more hierarchical organizations, and
incidentally
the advance of technology has been accompanied
by an
advance in the
science of
organization.
It's
now possible to
make organizations on
a
larger
scale
than was ever
possible
before.
And
so
that you have more and more people living their
lives
out as
subordinates
in these hierarchical systems controlled by
bureaucracies, either
bureaucracies
of big business or the
of
big
government.
Now, the devices
that you were
talking
about,
are
there
specific
devices
or
methods
of
communication
which
diminish
our
freedoms
in
addition
to
overpopulation
and
overorganization?
There
are
certainly devices which can
be
used in this way.
I
mean, let
us
take
our broad piece of very recent and very painful history
as
the
propaganda used by
Hitler,
which
was
incredibly
effective.
I
mean,
what were Hitler's
methods?
Hitler
used Terra on
the one
kind,
brute
force
on
the one
hand.
He
also
used a very efficient form of propaganda, which he
was using every modern device at that time. He
didn't have TV, but he had the radio which he used to
the fullest
extent.
And
was
able
to impose
his
will
on an immense mass
of
people, I
mean, the Germans were highly
educated people, for
we're aware of all
this, but how do we
equate Hitler's use of propaganda for the way that propaganda, if you will, is used,
let us say, here in
the
United
States?
Are you
suggesting
that
the
parallel,
not
being
used
in
this
way?
No,
but
the point is it seems
to me
that there
are methods present available, methods superior
in
some
respects
to
Hitler's
method, which could
be used in
a
bad
situation.
I
mean,
what I feel very strongly
is
that
we
mustn't
be
caught by
surprise
by
our own
advancing
technology.
It
happened
to gain
and again in history, with technology
as
advance,
and this
changes
social condition. And suddenly people have
found themselves in a situation which they didn't foresee and doing all sorts of things they didn't really want to
do.
Well,
now
what
do you
mean?
Do you mean that we develop our
television,
but
we
don't
know
how
to use it
correctly?
Is that
the
point
that you're making?
The
television, I think, is being used quite harmlessly. It's being used, I think. I would feel it's being used too much to
distract
everybody all the
time.
But
I
mean, imagine, which must be the situation in all communist countries, where the television, where it exists, is always saying the same
thing, the whole
time, is always
driving
along.
It's not creating a wide front of distraction. It's
creating a
one-pointed, drumming
in, with a single idea all the time. It's obviously
an
immensely
powerful
instrument.
So
you're
talking about the
potential
misuse
of the
instrument.
Exactly.
We
have,
after all, technology is
in
itself
marveled in
useful. These
are just
powers
which
can
either be used well
or
real.
It's the same thing with atomic energy. We can either use it to
blow ourselves up or we can use it as a substitute for the coal
and the oil which
we're
running
out.
You've
even written about
the
use of
drugs in
this
life.
Well,
now this is a
very
interesting
subject.
In this book,
if you mention this book of mine, Brave New
World, I postulated a substance called
Soma,
which
was
a
very
versatile
drug.
It
makes people feel happy in small
doses. It would make them see visions in medium doses and it
would send
them to
sleep in
large
doses.
Well,
I
don't think
such
a
drug
exists
now. I know it
will
ever exist, but we
do have drugs
which
will
do some of
these
things.
I
think it's
quite
on the
cards that we
may
have
drugs
which
will
profoundly
change
our
mental
states without
doing
us any
harm.
This
is
the
pharmacological
revolution
which has taken place.
We
have now
powerful
mind-changing
drugs
which
physiologically
speaking
are
almost
costly.
They are
not like opium
or
like cocaine which do change the
state of
mind but
to
leave
terrible
results
physiologically
and
morally.
Mr.
Huxley, in your new
essays
you
state
that these various enemies are
pushing us toward
a
real life Brave
New World and
you say that it's
awaiting
us
just
around
the
corner.
First
of
all, can you
detail
for us what life
in this Brave New World which
you fear so much of what
life might
be
like?
Well,
to
start
with,
I think
this kind of the dictatorship of the future, I think we're
very
unlike
the
dictatorships which
we've
been
familiar
with
in
the
immediate
past.
I
mean, take
another
book
prophesying the
future
which
was a very
remarkable
book, George
Orwell's
1984.
This
book was written
at the height
of the study
in East
Rageem and just after the Hitler regime and there
he
foresaw a
dictatorship
using
entirely the
methods
of
terror,
methods
of
physical
violence.
Now,
I think
what is
going to
happen in the future is that
dictators will find, as the old saying goes, that you can do everything with bear and it's except sit
on
them.
But
if
you
want
to preserve
your power indefinitely, you have to get the consent
of the rule
and this they will do
part
of
by
drugs
as
I
also
in
Brave
New
World,
part
of
these
new
techniques
of
propaganda.
They will
do it by bypassing the
rational side
of man
and appealing to his subconscious and his deeper
emotions
and
his physiology
even.
And
so
making
him
actually
love
his
slavery.
I
mean,
think
this
is
the
danger
that
actually
people
may
be
in
some
ways
happy
under
the
new
regime.
But they
will
be happy in
situation where they open to be
happy. But let
me
ask
you this.
You're talking
about a world that
could take place within the
confines of a totalitarian
state.
Let's become more
immediate, more urgent about it. We believe anyway
that
we live in
democracy
here
in
the
United
States.
Do
you
believe that this Brave New World
that you
talk
about
could,
let's
say
in
the
next
quarter
century,
the
next century.
Could
come
here
to our show us. I
think it could. I mean, that's why
I feel
it's so extremely important here and now to start thinking about these problems, not to let ourselves be taken by
surprise
by the
new
advances
in
technology.
I
mean,
the example in regard to the use of the drugs,
we know
there's enough evidence now for us to
be able on the basis
of this evidence and using a certain amount of creative imagination to foresee the kind of uses which could be made by people of bad will with these things and to attempt to to
forestall
this.
And
in the same
way,
I think with
these other
methods of
propaganda, we can foresee and we can do a good deal to
forestall.
I mean,
after the price of freedom
is eternal
vigilance.
You
write in enemies
of
freedom.
You
write
specifically
about the
United
States.
You say this,
writing about American
political
campaigns.
You
say all
that is needed is money and
the candidate who can be coached to look
sincere
political
principles
and plans for specific action have
come to lose most
of
their
importance.
The
personality
of
the
candidate,
way
he
is
projected
by
the
advertising
experts,
other
things
that
really
matter.
Well,
this
is
during
the
last campaign, there
was a great deal
of this
kind
of statement by the advertising managers of the campaign parties. This idea that the candidates had to be merchandise
as though they
were so
poor
toothpaste
and that
you had to depend entirely
on
the
personality.
I
mean, the
personality is
important, but there
are certainly people with an extremely
amiable personality, particularly on
TV, who might
not necessarily
be
very
good
in
political
positions
of
political
trust.
What do
you
feel
of men like
Eisenhower, Stevenson, Nixon, with knowledge of
thought, were trying to pull the world over the eyes of the American
public?
No,
but
they
were
being
advised
by
powerful advertising
agencies who were making
campaigns of
a
quite
different
kind
from what
had
been
made
before.
And
I think
we should
see
probably
all kinds
of
new devices
coming
into
the
picture.
For
example,
this
thing which got a
good
deal
of publicity
last
autumn, subliminal
projection. I mean, as it stands, this thing I think is of no menace
at the moment, but I was talking the other day to one of the people who has done most experimental work in the psychological laboratory
with this, who were saying precisely
this, that it is not at the
moment of
danger.
But
once you've established
a principle that something
works, you
can be absolutely
sure that
the
technology
of it is going to improve
steadily.
And
I
mean, his view of
the subject was
that, well, maybe they will use it
to
some
extent
in the 1960
campaign, but they will probably use it a good deal and
much more effectively in the 1964 campaign, because this is
the kind of rate at which
technology
advances.
And
we'll be
persuaded to vote for a
candidate that we do not know that we are being persuaded to vote
for.
Exactly.
I mean, this
is the rather alarming each of this.
You're being
persuaded
below
the
level
of
choice
and
reason.
In
regard
to
advertising,
which you
mentioned just
a
little
ago,
in
your
writing, particularly in enemies of
freedom, you attack
Madison
Avenue,
which
controls
most
of
our
television
and
radio
advertising,
newspaper
advertising
and so
forth.
Why
do
you
consistently
attack the advertising agency?
Well, no, I think that the
British
players
are very necessary to
row,
but
the
danger
seems
to
me in
a
democracy
is
this.
I
mean, what does
a
democracy depend
on?
A
democracy
depends
on
the
individual
voter
making
an intelligent and rational choice for
what he regards as his enlightened
self-interest
in
any
given
circumstance.
What
these
people
are
doing,
I
mean, what both, but
their
particular purposes
are
selling goods
and
the
dictatorial
propaganda
is
to
try
bypass
the
rational
side
of
men
and
to
appeal
directly
to
these
unconscious
forces
below
the
surface.
So that you are
in
a
way
making
nonsense
of
the
whole democratic
procedure, which
is based on
conscious
choice
of
rational
ground.
Of
course, well, maybe
you have just answered this next question because in your
essay, you
write about
television
commercials, not
just
political
commercials,
but
television
commercials
as
such.
And
how has
you put
it
today's children
walk around singing beer commercials and
tooth-faced commercials? And then you link this phenomenon in some way with
the dangers of
a
dictatorship.
Now, could you spell out
the
connection
or how
do you
feel
that
you
have
done so sufficiently?
Well, I mean,
yeah, this
whole
question of children, I think,
is a terribly
important one because children are quite clearly much more suggestible
than
the
average
grown-up.
And
again, suppose
that for one reason or another,
all the
propaganda was
in
the hands of one or
very
few
agencies.
You
would have an extraordinarily powerful
force playing
on these children, who
are probably going
to
grow up and be
adults
quite
soon.
I
do think that this
is
not
an immediate
threat, but
it remains a
possible
threat.
And you
said
something to the effect in your essay that the children of
Europe used to be called cannon
fodder,
and
here in the United States they
are television and radio
fodder.
Well,
after all
the
interview, you can
read
in the trade journal the most political accounts of how
necessary
it is to get hold
of the children because then they will be loyal brand
buyers
later
on.
But
I
mean, again, you've
just translated
this into political terms. The dictator says they will be loyal ideology buyers when they're
grown-up.
We
hear
so
much about brainwashing
as
used by
the communists. Do you see any
brainwashing other than that, which we've just been talking about, that is used here in the United States? Are
the
forms of
brainwashing?
Not in
the
form that has
been
used
in China and
in
Russia,
because
this
is essentially
the
application
of
propaganda
methods
must
burn
and kind
of
individuals.
It's
not a shotgun
method like
the
advertising
method.
It's a way of getting hold of the person and playing both on his physiology and his psychology, it really breaks
down and then you can implant a new idea in
his
head.
I
mean,
the descriptions
of the methods are
really
blood
curdling when
you
read
them.
Not
only the methods applied to
political
prisoners, but
the methods
applied, for example,
to the training of the young
communist administrators and
missionaries.
They
receive
an
incredibly
tough
kind of training, which may cause about
25% of them to break down or commit suicide, but produces 75% of completely
one-pointed
phonetics.
The
question, of
course, that keeps
coming back to my
mind is this. Obviously, politics in themselves are
not
evil.
Television
is
not
in
itself
evil.
Atomic energy
is
not
evil.
And yet you seem
to fear that it will be
used
in an evil way.
Why
is it
that the right people will not, in
your
estimation,
use
them?
Why
is
it
that the wrong
people
will
use
these
various
devices
and
for
the
wrong
motives?
Well,
I
think one of the
reasons is that these are all instruments
for obtaining
power. And obviously, the passion for power is one of the most moving passions that exist in
man.
And
I
draw this as
all
democracies are
based on
the
proposition that power is very dangerous, and that it's
extremely important not to let any one man or any one small group have
too
much
power
for
too
long
a
time.
And then, what
are the British and American
constitutions except devices
for limiting
power? And all these new devices are extremely efficient instruments for the imposition
of power by small groups of a larger
message.
Well,
you
ask
this
question
yourself. In enemies of freedom, I'll put your own question back to you. You ask this. In an age of accelerating
overpopulation, of accelerating
overorganization, and ever more efficient means of mass communication, how can we preserve the integrity
and reassert
the
value
of
the
human
individual?
You put the
question.
Now, here's your chance
to
answer it, Mr.
Huxen.
Well, this
is
obviously,
first of all, it's a
question of
education. I
think
it's
terribly important
to
insist
on
individual
values.
I
mean,
what
is
there is a
tendency as you've
probably read a book
by
White, the
organization
man, a very interesting, valuable
book, I
think, where
he
speaks
about the
new
type
of group
morality,
group
ethic,
which
speaks
about
the
group
as
though
the
group
was
somehow
more
important
than
the
individual.
But
this
seems
as far as
I'm concerned to be
in
contradiction
with what
we know about the
genetical makeup of
human
beings,
that
every
human
being
is
unique.
And
it is, of
course,
on
this
genetic
basis
that
the
whole
idea
of
the
value
of
freedom
is
based.
And
I
think
it's
extremely
important for us to stress this in all our educational life. And I would say it's also very
important to teach people to be on their guard against the sort of verbal
booby traps into which they're always being laid
to analyze the kind of
things that
are said
to
them.
But I think
there is this
whole
educational
side, and I think there are many more things that one could do to strengthen
people and to make them
more
aware of
what was being
done.
You're a prophet of
decentralization.
Well,
yes,
if this is feasible, it's one of the tragedies it seems
to me. I mean, many people have been talking
about the importance of decentralization in order to give back to the voter
a
sense
of
direct
power.
The
voter
in
an enormous
electorate
feels quite impotent, and his vote
seems to count
for
nothing. This
is not true where the electorate
is small and where
he is dealing
with
a
group
which
he
can
manage and
understand.
And if
one
can, as Jefferson after all
suggested,
break
up the
units into
smaller and
smaller
units.
So
get
a real
self-governing democracy. Well,
that
was all
very
well
in
Jefferson's
day,
but
how
can
we
revamp our
economic
system and
decentralize?
And
at
the
same
time,
meet
militarily and economically the tough challenge
of
a
country
like Soviet
Russia.
Well,
I
think
the answer
to that
is that there are, it seems to me that you are the production, industrial production is of two kinds. I mean, there are some kinds of industrial production, which obviously need the most tremendously high centralization, like the making of
autumn of
meals, for
example.
But
there
are
many other
kinds
where you could decentralize
quite
easily
and probably quite economically, and that you would then have this kind of decentralized life. I thought
you begin to see it now if you can travel through the south, this decentralized
textile
industry, which is bringing up
there.
Mr.
Huxel,
let
me ask you
this.
Quite
seriously.
Is
freedom
necessary?
As
far as I am concerned,
it
is.
Yes.
Is
it
necessary
for
a
productive
society?
Yes, I would say it is. I
mean,
genuinely
productive
is
that.
I
mean, I think
you could
produce
plenty
of goods without
much
freedom.
But
I
think the whole
sort
of creative
life of man
is
ultimately impossible without
a
considerable
measure
of
individual
freedom
of
initiative,
creation,
all
these
things which we
value.
And
I
think
that
you,
properly,
are
impossible
without
a
large
measure
of
freedom.
Well,
Mr.
Huxel,
take
a
look again at the country,
which is in the stance
of
our opponent
any way it
would seem
to be
there.
Soviet
Russia.
It
is
strong and
getting stronger,
economically,
militarily. At
the same
time,
it's
developing
its
art
forms
pretty
well.
It
seems not
unnecessarily to squelch the creative urge
among its
people,
and yet
it
is not a free
society.
It
is not
a
free
society, but
here
is something very
interesting
that
those
members
of
the society, like
the scientists who are doing
the creative work,
are given far more
freedom
than
anybody else.
I
mean,
it's
a privileged aristocratic
society
in which provided that they
don't poke
their
noses into political affairs,
these people are given a great deal of prestige, a considerable amount of freedom, and a lot
of
money.
I
mean,
this is a very interesting
fact about
the new
Soviet
regime.
And
I
think
we're going to see people on the whole with very little freedom, but with an oligarchy
on top, enjoying considerable measure of
freedom and a very
high standard of
living.
And the people
down below, the
epsilons
down
below,
enjoying
very
little.
And you think that that
kind
of
situation can long endure?
I
think it can certainly endure much
longer
than the
situation in which everybody is kept
down.
I mean,
they
can certainly get
their
technological and scientific
results
on
such a
basis.
Well,
the
next
time that
I
talk to
you
then,
perhaps
we
should
investigate
further
the
possibility
of
establishment
that
kind of
a
society,
where
the
drones
work for
the
Queen
bees
up
above.
Well,
with
years,
but
I
must say, I
still believe
in democracy if
we
can make the
best of all
the creative activities of the people on top, plus those of the people on the bottom so much the
better.
Mr.
Huxley, I surely
thank you for spending this half
hour with
us, and I
wish
you God's
speed,
sir.
Thank
you.
All
this
Huxley finds
himself
these days
in a peculiar and disturbing position, a quarter
of a century after prophesying an authoritarian state in which people were reduced to
Cyprus.
He
can
point at Soviet
Russia
and
say, I told you
so.
The
crucial question, as
he sees it
now,
is whether the so-called free
world is shortly going to give Mr. Huxley the further dubious satisfaction of
saying the same thing
about
us.
Stay
tuned for a preview of next week's interview.
Till then, my
qualis. Good
night.